This SQL video, which as
usual will consist mostly of
running live queries, introduces sub-queries in the where clause.
As usual, we start with our
basic select from where expression,
and we&#39;re going to add to it
now the ability in the
condition part of the select
from where expression to include sub-queries.
Sub-queries are nested, select
statements within the condition,
and we&#39;ll see they&#39;re actually quite powerful.
As usual, we&#39;ll be using a sample demonstration database that
consists of colleges, students, and students applying to colleges.
As always, we&#39;ll have our
four colleges, a bunch of
students, and a bunch of
records that show students applying to colleges.
So let&#39;s launch right
into our first query that shows
a sub-query in the where clause.
What this query finds is the
ID&#39;s and names of all students
who have applied to major in CS to some college.
So here&#39;s the sub-query in the where clause.
This expression right here in
the where clause finds the
ID&#39;s of all students who
have applied to major in CS.
So now we have that set of ID&#39;s,
our outer query says let&#39;s
take from the students those
students whose ID is in
that set, and let&#39;s select
their ID and their name.
So we go ahead and execute
the query and we find out
that five students have applied to major in CS.
Now we actually can do
this query without a sub-query in the where clause.
So let&#39;s take a look.
We can do it instead by joining
the student relation with the apply relation.
So here we do what we learned in previous videos.
We take student and apply, we
write the joined condition to make
sure we&#39;re talking about the same
student, we make sure
they&#39;re majoring in CS, and
we get their ID and their name.
Let&#39;s run the query.
Whoops, an error.
I knew that was coming.
This is just to remind you about disambiguating attributes.
The ID here in the
select clause could have come
from student or apply, and
even though the value is equal,
we do have to disambiguate by putting one of those.
So let&#39;s put student dot SID
and let&#39;s run the query.
Okay.
Now we see we got more
students back than we
got back when we ran the query using the sub-query.
Let&#39;s go back and look.
We got five results here and
we got several more here,
but the additional results are actually duplicate values.
So we have two copies, for example, of 1-2-3 Amy.
The reason for that is
that Amy actually applied to
major in CS at multiple colleges.
So if we go back and we
look at the apply data, we&#39;ll
see that Amy who is
1-2-3 applied to major in CS
at Stanford as well as Berkeley.
Let&#39;s hope she selects Stanford.
In any case, that&#39;s
why we got Amy twice in
the join because she applied twice.
Back here where we used
the sub-query, we were just
looking at students and whether their ID was in the set.
Okay, so when we do
the join we get basically the
same answer, but we have some duplicate values.
Of course, we can fix that by adding distinct.
We run the query and now
we have the same result that we got when we used the sub-query.
Let&#39;s look at some other
similar queries and let&#39;s
focus again on the duplicates
issue because it gets a little tricky, as we&#39;ll see.
This query is very similar
to the previous one, finding students
who are applying to major in
CS, but this time
we&#39;re only getting the names of
the students and not their ID&#39;s.
So we run the query and we find our same five students.
Just want to mention that these
two Craigs are two different Craigs.
If we go back to our
original result, there&#39;s three-four-five Craig
and five-four-three Craig.
So coming back here, we
find the names of the
students who majored in CS.
Now similarly to what we
did previously, let&#39;s write this
query using a join instead
of using the sub-query in the where clause.
So here&#39;s the join.
We&#39;re joining student and apply
on the student&#39;s ID majoring in CS, as always.
The only difference is that we&#39;re just selecting the name.
We run the query and we
get again many more results
than we got previously because we
get two copies when a
student has applied to to
major in CS at two different places.
And just as we
did before, we can add distinct to get rid of the duplicates.
Well, something different happened this time.
This time, when we get
rid of the duplicates, we only have
four results where previously we had five.
And the reason is that previously
we included the student ID
in the result, and so the
two instances of Craig were
two different Craigs and didn&#39;t
cause duplicates to be eliminated.
We can see that back here: Craig and Craig.
But in this result, because we
only kept the names, the two
copies of Craig turned into one result.
Now we might wonder why
do we care about duplicates so much.
Let&#39;s see an example where duplicates really do matter quite a bit.
We&#39;re going to do exactly the same
query again, finding students who
have applied to major in CS,
but now we&#39;re not retrieving the
IDs or names, we&#39;re retrieving
the GPAs of those students.
Presumably what we&#39;re interested in
doing is some analysis of the
GPA&#39;s of students who choose to apply for CS.
So let&#39;s run the query.
As always, we get our five results.
And here&#39;s the GPA&#39;s of the
five students who have applied to major in CS.
Once again, this will be
the last time, I promise, we&#39;ll
do this query using a join instead of the sub-query.
So here we go.
We&#39;ve got student and apply join
on SID, majoring in CS, and returning the GPA.
Once again, because we
have students who applied multiple
times for CS, we&#39;re getting more than our five results.
So we get a rather large number
of results here and again we have duplicates.
So here&#39;s where the problem comes in.
If we use this result to
compute the average GPA, we&#39;ll be
counting some students multiple times.
And presumably, that&#39;s not what we want to do.
Presumably, we want to count
each student who&#39;s applied to
CS once in the computation
of, say, the average GPA.
That worked in the previous query
when we got the five results for the five students who applied to CS.
When we do the join, we get too many results.
But this time, again, we&#39;re
going to have a problem when we
do select distinct, because some
of these students have the same GPA.
And now we only have
four GPAs instead of the five that we should have.
And if we compute the
average GPA now, then we&#39;re
not factoring in one of the student&#39;s GPAs.
So in this case, neither the
version with distinct nor the
version without distinct gives us
the right number of GPAs.
Neither of those will give us the correct average.
The only way to get the
correct number of duplicates is
to use the version of the
query that has the sub-query in the where clause.
Now let&#39;s move to some different
examples that also use subqueries in the where clause.
You might remember from
the previous video when we
were learning the difference operator that
we had a query that we
could write using the difference operator,
which in SQL is called except,
but we were unable to
write that query without the difference operator.
And the query we were trying to
write is to find students
who have applied to major in
CS, but have not applied to major in EE.
Now that we have sub-queries in
the where clause, we can write
that query without using the except operator.
And here it is.
The query looks for students where
their ID is among the
set of ID&#39;s of students
who have applied to CS, but
their ID is not among
the set of ID&#39;s of students
who are applying to major in EE.
So let&#39;s run the query.
And we discover that
there are three students who have
applied to major in CS,
but not applied anywhere in EE.
By the way, let me just show
you a slightly different way to write exactly the same query.
You can see that we use this
key word combination &quot;not in&quot;
to specify that the ID is not in this set.
We can actually write it by
writing the SID is
in the set and then applying a &quot;not&quot; to that result.
We&#39;ll execute and we&#39;ll get exactly the same result.
It&#39;s fairly common in SQL
for there to be multiple ways to
write the same query, and we&#39;ll
see more examples of that later in this video.
So far, our examples
of sub-queries have used &quot;in&quot;
and &quot;not in&quot; for testing
membership in the sets that are produced by sub-queries.
Our next examples are going
to show that we can apply
the exists operator to sub-queries
just to test whether they&#39;re empty or not empty.
Here&#39;s the query.
This query uses exists to check
whether a subquery is empty
or not empty rather than checking
whether values are in the subquery.
The other new construct that&#39;s
begin to introduce here&#39;s what&#39;s known as a correlated reference.
But inside the subquery we&#39;re going
to refer to a value,
C1, that comes from outside the subquery.
So let&#39;s talk about exactly how this query works.
First let me tell you what the query is trying to return.
The query is going to find
all colleges, such that there&#39;s
some other college that is in the same state.
Okay?
So, in our example, just a
reminder, we have Stanford, Berkeley, MIT and Cornell.
So, the two Colleges we should
get back are Stanford and Berkeley
because in each case there&#39;s another
college in the same state.
So how does this query work?
It says we&#39;re gonna to take
the colleges, and for
each college we&#39;re going to
check whether their exists another
college and we&#39;re going to
call that one C2, where the
state of C2 is the same as the state of C1.
This is sort of similar
to what we saw when were
doing self-joins with table variables,
but now, the variables are
appearing in the outer query and the inner query.
Okay.
So, let&#39;s run the query and
we see that we get the wrong answer.
That was again intentional.
Well, here&#39;s the problem.
When we were in this query, C1
and C2 could be bound to the same college.
So every college is in
the same state as another college
of the other college could be the same college.
What we need to do is
add inside the sub-query a
further condition that says that C1 and C2 are different colleges.
Specifically, C1.Cname
is not equal to C2.Cname.
Let&#39;s run the query
and now, we get the correct answer.
Now, let&#39;s look at some
other uses of the exists,
construct and sub-query.
If you happen to already know SQL
a little bit and someone
asks you to write a query
where you were going going to
get a largest value of some type,
the first thing you would think of
is probably using the max operator,
but we don&#39;t know max yet, we&#39;ll be learning that later videos.
And as it happens, a number of
queries that are effectively computing
a max can be written using sub-queries.
And here&#39;s our first example.
This example is finding the college that has the largest enrollment.
And we&#39;re going to
do that with the sub-query and with the not-exists operator.
Specifically, we&#39;re going to
find all colleges where there
does not exist another college
whose enrollment is higher than the first college.
So let&#39;s go ahead and run the query.
And, not surprisingly, we get Berkeley as a result.
So this is a form of
query that we can write any
time we&#39;re looking for something that&#39;s the largest or the smallest.
Let&#39;s, for example, look for
the student with the highest GPA.
So we&#39;ll change it to
the student name, and we&#39;ll
be looking instead of colleges at students.
Otherwise this form of this query is going to stay very similar.
We&#39;re going to look for students here as well.
And finally, we&#39;re going to have GPA instead of enrollment.
So, the way this query
works is it says &quot;I want
to find all students, such that
there does not exist another student
who&#39;s GPA is higher&quot;.
We run the query and we get four results.
Seems odd.
Actually it&#39;s not that odd.
Let&#39;s just add the GPA to our query and we&#39;ll see exactly what happened.
We can see that these four
students all have a GPA
of 3.9, so they&#39;re all tied for
having the highest GPA and very
specifically it faithfully runs the
query that there does not
exist another student whose
GPA is higher than these students.
Now, let&#39;s see if
we can write this same query without using a sub query.
So as usual, if we
want to write a query without
a sub query, we&#39;ll need to do some type of joint.
So we&#39;re looking for students with the highest GPAs.
So, we need to join two
instances of the student relation
as we&#39;ve done here and then
we&#39;ll apply a condition that
the GPA of the first one
is greater than the GPA of the second one.
We run the query.
Wow, we got a lot of answers there.
Maybe our problem is just
one of duplicates. So first thing
we do when it looks too big
we add select distinct. Nope,
that doesn&#39;t solve the problem either.
Actually this query is fundamentally wrong
and we cannot write the query
that finds the student with the
highest GPA just by using joins.
What this query actually does is
it finds all students such
that there is some other student whose GPA is lower.
In other words, it&#39;s finding all
students except those who have the lowest GPA.
Now let&#39;s see another
new construct we can use
with sub-queries in the where
clause and we&#39;ll continue with
the same query of finding the student with the highest GPA.
This query uses the all keyword.
What all tells us is that
instead of checking whether a
value is either in or
not in the result of a
sub-query, we&#39;re going to
check whether the value has a
certain relationship with all the results of the sub-query.
And here, in this case, we&#39;re
checking to see if the
GPA is greater than or
equal to all elements
of the sub-query that returns the GPA&#39;s of all students.
If the student&#39;s GPA is indeed
greater than or equal to all
GPA&#39;s then the student has the highest GPA in the database.
We&#39;ll run the query, and we&#39;ll
get the same four students with the 3.9 GPA.
Now, let&#39;s try writing
this in a slightly different fashion
just for fun to illustrate some concepts.
Once again, we&#39;re going to
try to find the students whose GPA is highest in the database.
Here&#39;s how we&#39;re going to do it this time.
Instead of using greater than or
equal to all, we&#39;re going to use greater than all.
So, we&#39;re going to find all students
where their GPA is higher than every other student
by saying GPA is greater than
all GPA&#39;s of students
in the database who are not the student we&#39;re looking at.
By saying that the ID&#39;s are not equal.
Let&#39;s run the query.
Well, we got an empty result.
Let&#39;s think about it for a second.
That is actually the correct result to the query.
The query itself was incorrect.
The query is looking for all
students where nobody else
has the same GPA as that student.
Everybody else&#39;s GPA is lower. Well,
remember, we had four students
with a 3.9 GPA, so
none of those students are going
to satisfy the query and nor will any other student.
So this is an incorrect formulation of the query that we wanted.
Now this query would be
correct if we knew
that every student had the same GP...I&#39;m sorry.
This query would be correct if
we knew that every student&#39;s GPA was
unique, because there would be
then one student who had the highest GPA.
So let&#39;s modify the query
to instead look for the
colleges that have the highest enrollment.
Because it turns out in our database every college has a unique enrollment.
So we&#39;ll change it to
getting the C name of college instead of student.
And we&#39;ll want the enrollment to
be greater than all other enrollments.
So we&#39;ll...enrollment, college, almost done here.
Grab a cup of coffee if you want.
I just have to make this
be C name and this
one be C name and we&#39;re all set.
So what are we asking for here?
We&#39;re asking for all colleges whose
enrollment is greater than all
of the enrollments of colleges that
are different than the one we&#39;re looking at.
We run the query and we get
Berkeley as a result
which is exactly what we&#39;d expect.
So far we&#39;ve seen the keyword
all for checking whether a
value has relationship with all of the results of a sub query.
There&#39;s also a key word
any that is a
companion but instead of
having to satisfy a condition
with all of the elements of
a set any says you
must satisfy the condition with
at least one element of the set.
So what we&#39;re going to do
now is going to do
the same query but we&#39;re gonna write it a little differently.
Let me just type it in and then explain.
Here what we&#39;re going to
say is get me all colleges
where it&#39;s not the case
that the enrollment is less
than or equal to any other college.
Okay?
So in other words there&#39;s no other colleges have bigger enrollment.
Just think about it for
a second, this is if you happen to know predicate logic.
This is an equivalence where when
you say for all it&#39;s equivalent
to not exists not.
In any case if you didn&#39;t follow that don&#39;t let that bother you.
Let&#39;s run the query and we
see we again get the result
Berkeley, so again all
tests a condition against every
element in the result of a
sub query, and the condition
is true if it&#39;s satisfied with
every element; whereas any is
true if the condition is satisfied with one or
more elements of the sub-query.
Let&#39;s use any for another query.
This query finds all students
who are not from the smallest high school in the database.
So, what we are looking for
here is all students, where the
size of their high school
is greater than any high school size.
In other words, a student is
going to be returned if there&#39;s
some other student whose size
high school is smaller than this student.
We run the query, and there&#39;s the result.
And you can verify if you
look back at the data, but
there is in fact, a few,
there are students who are
from high schools that have 200
students, so here, we
have in our result every
student that comes from a high school bigger than that.
Some systems, notably at
the current time SQLite, do
not support the any and the all operators.
We do not lose expressive power, we
just have to write those queries
a little differently typically using exist
or not exists, so let&#39;s
look at the same query written without using any.
Here&#39;s what we do.
We look for students where there
exists some other student,
okay, whose high school is
smaller than the student we returned.
So this is going to give us
exactly the same result and
we will see we will get the same set of students.
No students from a high
school with two hundred but we
get all the rest of the
students without using any or all.
And just to emphasize, any or
all are very convenient for writing queries, but they aren&#39;t necessary.
It turns out we can always write
a query that would use
any or all by using the
exists operator or not exists instead.
As a grand finale query, let&#39;s
revisit the query that finds
students who have applied to major
CS and have not applied to major in EE.
And now we&#39;re going to write
that query using the any
operator, two instances of it.
Now let&#39;s go back and look
when we wrote the query using in
and not in, and we see
that there are three results, Helen, Irene and Craig.
And now let&#39;s look at
our query using any and not equal to any.
So we find students where their
SID is in the set
of SID&#39;s of students who have
applied to major in CS and
their SID is not equal to
any of the students who
have applied to major in EE and let&#39;s run the query.
Well we got the wrong
answer and that was once again intentional.
Let&#39;s look very closely at what this query asks for.
This query asks for students
students where their ID is in
the set of ID&#39;s that
applied to CS, that&#39;s all fine
and good but this is where things got tricky.
What we&#39;re saying here is
that we want
the condition to check whether
there&#39;s any element in the
set of EE&#39;s that are
not equal to this SID.
So, in fact, this second condition
is satisfied as long as
there&#39;s anybody who applied to
EE that&#39;s not equal to
the student we&#39;re looking at and
that of course is commonly the case,
so we made a mistake
here and it&#39;s actually quite tricky
to use the any and
all operators and always get the right answer.
It&#39;s especially tricky when you
can&#39;t just eyeball the answer
and check but the correct
formulation that we want
here is that it&#39;s not
the case that the SID
is equal to any member of the set.
In other words, for each member
of the set of the EE
application, that value is
not equal to the SID
of the student we&#39;re going to retrieve.
And now we run the query and we get the right answer.